<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section xml:id="cmdWriteDB"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<info>
  <title>Writing the call-sign DB</title>
</info>

<para>
  The command line interface also allows to write a call-sign DB (also known as <glossterm>Talker 
  Alias</glossterm>)to the radio if the radio supports it. This can be done with the 
  <command>write-db</command> command. This command behaves similar to the call-sign DB upload in 
  <application>qdmr</application>. That is, it tries to select the call-signs being written 
  automatically.
</para>

<para>
  Although many radios provide a huge amount of memory for the call-sign DB, they cannot hold the 
  entire list of assigned DMR IDs. Therefore a selection of relevant call-signs must be done. 
  <application>qdmr</application> and <command>dmrconf</command> do that based on the DMR ID of
  the radio. DMR IDs are not random. They follow a pattern similar to land-line phone numbers. DMR
  IDs within a certain continent, country and region share a common prefix. This way, it is 
  possible to select DMR IDs that are <emphasis>close</emphasis> by selecting IDs that share a 
  common prefix. 
</para>

<para>
  <application>qdmr</application> and <command>dmrconf</command> therefore uses the default DMR ID
  of the radio to select the call-signs to be written. This ID is obtained by 
  <application>qdmr</application> from the codeplug. <command>dmrconf</command> does not require a
  codeplug to be present for the upload. Consequently, it requires the explicit specification 
  of the ID to base the selection on. The ID can be specified using the <option>--id</option> or 
  <option>-I</option> options. It is also possible to just specify the prefix instead of an ID.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf write-db --id=2621]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This example writes a call-sign DB to the connected radio using the DMR prefix 2621 (for the 
  region Berlin/Brandenburg in Germany). The radio will fill the available space with as many 
  call-signs as possible. So for the previous example, <command>dmrconf</command> will not only
  program all IDs with the prefix 2621 but as many as possible starting with those 
  <emphasis>close</emphasis> to that prefix. It is possible to limit the number of call-sign 
  encoded using the <option>--limit</option> or <option>-n</option> option.
</para>

<para>
  Unfortunately, there is always an exception to a rule: Some countries have several prefixes or
  you may program the call-signs of several countries that are not necessarily 
  <emphasis>close</emphasis> in terms of their prefixes. For these cases, it is possible to 
  specify a list of prefixes to the <option>--id</option> option.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf write-db --id=262,263 --limit=10000]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This example will select and write up to 10000 (given the radio can hold that amount) 
  call-signs staring with those <emphasis>closest</emphasis> to the prefixes 262 and 263
  (both prefixes for Germany).
</para>

<section xml:id="cmdEncodeDB">
<info><title>Encoding a call-sign DB</title></info>

<para>
  Like for the binary codeplug, it is also possible to generate and store the binary representation
  of the call-sign DB using the <command>encode-db</command> command. This command is only useful 
  for debugging purposes as the binary representation of the call-sign DB cannot be written to the
  device.
</para>

<para>
  The <command>encode-db</command> takes the same arguments as the <command>write-db</command> 
  command but additionally needs a filename to store the encoded DB into as well as the radio
  to encode for using the <option>--radio</option> option.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf encode-db --radio=d878uv --id=262,263 --limit=10000 callsigns.dfu]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  Like the previous example, this one encodes up to 10000 call-signs starting with those closest to
  the prefixes 262 and 263 for a AnyTone AT-D878UV radio and stores the result into 
  <filename>callsigns.dfu</filename>.
</para>
</section>
</section>