<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section xml:id="cmdCodeplug"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<info>
  <title>Reading and writing codeplugs</title>
</info>

<para>
  The major feature of the command line tool is certainly the ability to read and write codeplugs 
  from and to the device. The majority of the action happens automatically. Like the detection of
  the radio. If something goes wrong, an error message will be written to <varname>stderr</varname>. 
  A more detailed logging can be enabled by passing the <option>--debug</option> flag.
</para>


<section xml:id="cmdRead">
<info><title>Reading a codeplug</title></info>
<para>
  To read a codeplug, the <command>read</command> command is used. The codeplug can be stored in 
  several formats. The human readable extensible codeplug format (YAML), the old table based format
  and as a binary memory dump of the codeplug memory on the device. 
  <command>dmrconf</command> detects the format based on the file extension or by means of additional 
  flags. The latter is particularly important if the read codeplug should be written to 
  <varname>stdout</varname> for piping it to another program for further processing.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting language="bash"><![CDATA[dmrconf read codeplug.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  Will simply read the codeplug from the detected device and stores it in the extensible codeplug 
  format in the file <filename>codeplug.yaml</filename>. The format was detected by the file 
  extension <filename>yaml</filename> which refers to the extensible codeplug format using YAML.
</para>

<para>
  The same call with a file name <filename>codeplug.conf</filename> would store the codeplug in the
  old table based <filename>conf</filename> format.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
    Not that the latter is way less expressive and does not support the storage of device specific 
    settings. This format is basically kept for backwards compatibility and should not be used 
    anymore.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
  To store the memory dump of the codeplug memory of the radio, the file extension should be 
  <filename>dfu</filename>. 
</para>

<para>
  As mentioned above, it is also possible to dump the decoded codeplug to <varname>stdout</varname> 
  allowing to pipe the codeplug into another program for processing. This can be done by omitting 
  the output filename. Then, however, the output format is not specified anymore. In this case, one
  the explicit format flags <option>--yaml</option>, <option>--csv</option> or 
  <option>--bin</option> must be used to specify in which format the codeplug should be written. 
  These flags can also be used to store a codeplug in a particular format in arbitrarily named 
  files. 
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf read --yaml | python my_script.py]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>
<para>
  This example reads the codeplug from the connected device and decodes it. The decoded codeplug is
  then piped to the python script <filename>my_script.py</filename>. 
</para>


<section xml:id="cmdDecode">
<info><title>Decoding binary codeplugs</title></info>
<para>
  It is also possible decode binary codeplugs that has been read from the device earlier and 
  stored as a memory dump (i.e., in a <filename>dfu</filename> file). This step is actually
  the second step automatically performed during reading. When reading a codeplug, in a first step
  the memory dump of the codeplug is read from the device. In a second step, the read binary 
  codeplug is then decoded and dumped in a human readable format. 
</para>

<para>
  The <command>decode</command> command then performs that second step. To do that, it needs
  two additional information: The radio type, from which this codeplug was read and the format
  to write the decoded format to. Like for the <command>read</command> command, the latter
  can be passed by the output filename extension or via an additional flag.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf read codeplug.dfu
dmrconf decode --radio=uv390 codeplug.dfu codeplug.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This example performs the same actions like a simple <command>read</command> command (assuming a
  TyT MD-UV390 is connected). It first downloads the binary codeplug. This time, the memory dump 
  is stored in a binary from (<filename>dfu</filename> file). The second command then decodes 
  the binary codeplug into the extensible codeplug format (<filename>yaml</filename> file), assuming 
  that the binary codeplug stems from a TyT MD-UV390.
</para>

<para>
  Since version 0.8.1, it is now also possible to decode some manufacturer binary codeplug files as
  they are produced by the manufacturer CPS. To signal the decode command to treat the file as a
  manufacturer CPS file, you need to pass the <option>-m</option> or <option>--manufacturer</option>
  and the <option>--radio</option> option. The latter tells the <command>decode</command> command 
  the format of the file. That is, the call
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf decode -m --radio=uv390 manufacturer_cps_file.rdt codeplug.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  Will decode the manufactuer CPS file <filename>manufacturer_cps_file.rdt</filename> assuming it 
  is a file generated by the CPS for the TyT MD-UV390. Like for the <quote>normal</quote> decoding
  the output format must be specified either by file extension or flag.
</para>


<section>
<info><title>Debugging the codplug decoding</title></info>
<para>
  Under normal circumstances, it makes no sense to first read the binary codeplug from the device 
  and then decoding it in a separate step as the read command will do that for you.
</para> 

<para>
  However, if there is a bug in <command>dmrconf</command> that gets triggered by your codeplug on 
  the device, the binary codeplug is an invaluable resource for debugging the application. Consider 
  filing an issue at the <link xlink:href="https://github.com/hmatuschek/qdmr/issues">bug 
  tracker</link> and include the binary codeplug as an attachment. 
</para>

<para>
  If you like, you can also send me your codeplug directly. I'll keep it confidentially.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>


<section>
<info><title>Writing a codeplug</title></info>

<para>
  To write a codeplug into the device, the <command>write</command> command is used. The codeplug
  can be read from several formates. The extensible codeplug format (<filename>yaml</filename> 
  file) as well as the old table based format (<filename>conf</filename> file). It is not possible
  to write binary codeplugs without decoding them first. Like for the <command>read</command> 
  command, <command>dmrconf</command> will detect the format based on the file extension or by 
  passed flags.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf write codeplug.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This example will write the codeplug stored in the extensible codeplug format in 
  <filename>codeplug.yaml</filename> to the connected device. Before writing the codeplug to the 
  device, the connected device gets detected and the codeplug gets verified.
</para>

<para>
  If the verification step fails, one or more error messages are written to 
  <varname>stderr</varname> describing the issue with the codeplug. One verification step is the
  check whether all channel frequencies are within the frequency limits specified by the 
  manufacturer. The latter check can be disabled using the 
  <option>--ignore-frequency-limits</option> flag.
</para>

<para>
  There are also some flags controlling the assembly of the binary codeplug. When the  
  <option>--init-codeplug</option> flag is set, the codeplug will be generated from scratch using
  default values for all options not explicitly specified in the codeplug file. This might be used
  to initialized a brand new radio. However, any changes made to the radio settings are lost. 
</para>

<para>
  When this option is not set, the codeplug gets encoded and written in a two-step process. First
  the current binary codeplug is downloaded from the radio. Then the codeplug file is used to 
  update the binary codeplug. The result is then written back to the device. This ensures that all
  settings made in the radio are kept, unless they are explicitly set in the codeplug file.
</para>

<para>
  The <option>--auto-enable-gps</option> and <option>--auto-enable-roaming</option> flags will 
  tell <command>dmrconf</command> to enable the GPS or roaming feature whenever any of the 
  programmed channels use the GPS or a roaming zone. (This depends also on the ability of the 
  radio.)
</para>

<section xml:id="cmdVerify">
<info><title>Verify a codeplug</title></info>
<para>
  The aforementioned verification of the codeplug file can also be performed separately using the
  <command>verify</command>. This command also needs to know against which radio the codeplug 
  should be verified. The radio must be specified using the <option>--radio</option> option.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf verify --radio=d878uv codeplug.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This command will verify the codeplug stored in <filename>codeplug.yml</filename> in the 
  extensible codeplug format against an AnyTone AT-D878UV. Like for the <command>write</command>, 
  any issues are written to <varname>stderr</varname>.
</para>

<para>
  Like for the <command>write</command> command, the verification can be altered using the
  <option>--ignore-frequency-limits</option> flag.
</para>
</section>


<section xml:id="cmdEncode">
<info><title>Encoding codeplugs</title></info>

<para>
  Is is also possible to perform the encoding step of the codeplug separately. This can be done
  with the <command>encode</command> command. Like for the <command>verify</command> command,
  the <command>encode</command> command also needs the radio for which the codeplug should be 
  encoded. The input format of the codeplug is again specified by either the file extension 
  of the codeplug file or by flags.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf encode --radio=opengd77 codeplug.yaml codeplug.dfu]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This call will encode the codeplug <filename>codeplug.yaml</filename> specified in the extensible
  codeplug format for a radio running the OpenGD77 firmware and stores the resulting binary 
  codeplug in <filename>codeplug.dfu</filename>.
</para>

<para>
  Like for the <command>write</command> command, the encoding can be controlled using the 
  <option>--auto-enable-gps</option> and <option>--auto-enable-roaming</option> flags.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>