<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section xml:id="cmdDangerZone"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<info>
  <title>Danger zone</title>
</info>

<warning>
  <para>
    You are about to enter the land of pain. Continue on your own risk.
  </para>
</warning>

<para>
  Some radios are actually identical to others. They also identify them self as a different radio.
  An example for such a radio is the Retevis RT3S, this radio is simply a relabeled TyT MD-UV390. 
  The RT3S actually identifies itself as a MD-UV390. From the perspective of the CPS, these two 
  radios are indistinguishable. Consequently, <application>qdmr</application> and 
  <command>dmrconf</command> will always identify the RT3S as a MD-UV390.
</para>

<para>
  There are, however, virtually identical radios. These are radios that actually identify them self
  as different models but the firmware, communication protocol and codeplug is basically identical 
  to another model. An example for such virtually identical models are the AnyTone AT-D868UV and 
  the BTech DMR-6X2. Each model identifies itself correspondingly and thus is distinguished by the
  CPS. Some of these relationships between virtually identical models are known to 
  <application>qdmr</application> and <command>dmrconf</command>. In these cases, the CPS will 
  treat these radios as identical.
</para>

<para>
  Some of these close relationships between models are not known to <command>dmrconf</command>. In 
  these cases, <command>dmrconf</command> will stop with an error that a radio is unknown although
  it actually supported as a different model. In these rare cases, it is possible to override the
  radio detection using the <option>--radio</option> option. 
</para>

<para>
  This option is usually used to specify the type whenever the radio model is not detected. This 
  option also overrides the model detection and thus allows to handle virtually identical radios.
  For example, if the relation ship between the AT-D868UV and the DMR-6X2 would have not been 
  known to <command>dmrconf</command>, a codeplug could read anyway from the device by calling
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf read --radio=d868uv codeplug_6x2.yaml]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  Here the radio detection (resulting the detection of a DMR-6X2) gets overridden and the radio is
  handled as a AT-D868UV. 
</para>

<para>
  If you know of such virtually identical radios that <command>dmrconf</command> does not 
  recognize, consider filing an issue at 
  <link xlink:href="https://github.com/hmatuschek/qdmr/issues">the bug tracker</link>.
</para>

<warning>
  <para>
    Of cause, handling a radio differently as it identifies itself may cause permanent damage to
    the radio. So you should be very sure that the radios are actually identical when overriding
    the radio detection routines.
  </para>
</warning>
</section>
