<?xml version="1.0"?>

<refentry xml:id="qdmr"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform">
  <refmeta>
    <refentrytitle>qdmr</refentrytitle>
    <manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
    <refmiscinfo class="source">qdmr</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="version">0.10.2</refmiscinfo>
    <refmiscinfo class="manual">User Commands</refmiscinfo>
  </refmeta>

  <info>
    <author>
      <personname><firstname>Hannes</firstname> <surname>Matuschek</surname></personname>
      <email>dm3mat@darc.de</email>
      <contrib>Main author</contrib>
    </author>
  </info>

  <refnamediv>
    <refname>qdmr</refname>
    <refpurpose>Graphical tool for programming DMR radios.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>

  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <cmdsynopsis>
      <command>qdmr</command>
      <arg choice="opt"><option>OPTIONS</option></arg>
      <arg choice="opt"><option>CODEPLUG_FILE</option></arg>
    </cmdsynopsis>
  </refsynopsisdiv>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Description</title>
    <para>
      <command>qdmr</command> is a graphical tool to program DMR radios.
      That is, reading, editing, generating and uploading codeplugs to these 
      radios. 
    </para>
    <para>
      The configuration of these radios is usually stored in a highly vendor
      and device specific binary codeplug. <command>qdmr</command> stores this
      configuration in a human-readable and device independent format, thus 
      allowing for sharing codeplugs across devices.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Options</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>CODEPLUG_FILE</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the optional codeplug file is passed to qdmr, it gets loaded on 
            startup. Otherwise, the application starts with an empty codeplug.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-style=STYLE</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows to set a Qt style for the application. This can
            be used to alter the style of the widgets. So call 
            <userinput>qdmr -style=windows</userinput> if you fancy.
          </para>
          <para>
            However, this option is of real use if you want to use a dark 
            theme. By installing a dark Qt theme like kvantum-dark and starting
            qdmr by passing this theme to the style option. That is
          </para>
          <screen>
            qdmr -style=kvantum-dark
          </screen>
          <para>
            You may set the Qt style for all Qt applications using the 
            <varname>QT_STYLE_OVERRIDE</varname> environment variable.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-stylesheet=FILENAME</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows for specifying a style sheet to alter the 
            appearance of some or all widgets of qdmr. </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <para>
      Qdmr writes a lot of debug and error messages to 
      <varname>stderr</varname>. This can be used to inspect some issues during
      reading/writing the a codeplug to the device. There is also a log file 
      containing these messages usually at 
      <filename>~/.local/share/DM3MAT/qdmr/qdmr.log</filename>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>

  <refsect1>
    <title>Bugs</title>
    <para>
      This program is still under development and may contain bugs that
      may cause harm to the radios and may even destroy them. Hence you may
      use this software on your own risk. If you want to have guaranties,
      consider using the CPS (code-plug programming software) supplied with
      your radio.
    </para>
    <para>
      There are some issues with the so-called dark mode under Linux. The Qt 
      library is not able to detect that the desktop has a dark mode theme. To
      this end, qdmr cannot react to it too. To enable a dark theme for qdmr, 
      see the <option>-style</option> option above.
    </para>
    <para>
      Writing a single application supporting several radios of different 
      manufacturers is a hard task. To this end, there are plenty of bugs to be
      expected. If you stumble across one of them, consider opening an issue at
      <ulink url="https://github.com/hmatuschek/qdmr/issues"/>.
    </para>
  </refsect1>
</refentry>
