<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section xml:id="cmdVarious"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<info>
  <title>Various features of <command>dmrconf</command></title>
</info>

<para>
  Beside reading and writing codeplugs or writing the call-sign DB, there are some more commands 
  and features that mainly concern the debugging of the codeplug and call-sign DB encoding and 
  decoding. If you are interested in the codeplug internals, you may use these commands to study
  them.
</para>


<section xml:id="cmdHelp">
<info><title>Getting help</title></info>

<para>
  As usual for command line tools, a brief help text about the commands and options gets written
  to <varname>stdout</varname> when the <option>--help</option> or <option>-h</option> option is 
  passed. No other commands passed are executed then.
</para>

<para>
  Similar to the <option>--help</option> option, it is possible to print the version number of 
  <command>dmrconf</command> using the <option>--version</option> or <option>-v</option> option.
  Like for the <option>--help</option>, no other commands passed get executed.
</para>

<para>
  To get a list of keys identifying radio models when specified using the <option>--radio</option>
  option, the <option>--list-radios</option> can be passed. This will print a small table to 
  <varname>stdout</varname> that lists the keys for each known radio as well as the model and
  manufacturer name.
</para>
</section>


<section xml:id="cmdDetect">
<info><title>Detecting the radio type</title></info>
<para>
  The command <command>detect</command> solely detects the radio. No data is written or read 
  from the device (except of the radio model information). This command can be used to check 
  whether a radio is detected correctly.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf detect]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This command will try to detect the connected radio. If a known radio is found, the model and
  manufacturer name is written to <varname>stdout</varname>. If no radio is detected or if the 
  model is unknown or unsupported, an error message is written to <varname>stderr</varname>.
</para>
</section>


<section xml:id="cmdInfo">
<info><title>Inspecting binary codeplugs</title></info>

<para>
  The <command>encode</command>, <command>encode-db</command> and <command>read</command> commands
  can store the codeplug and call-sign DB in binary form in a DFU file. The generated file is a 
  valid DFU (device firmware update) file, that can be handled with other DFU tools.
</para>

<para>
  A DFU file may contains several so-called images. Each image may contains several so-called 
  elements. The latter represents a segment of memory with an associated memory address. 
</para>

<para>
  The <command>info</command> command produces a hex-dump of the DFU file that is written to 
  <varname>stdout</varname>. It can then be inspected using <command>more</command> or 
  <command>less</command>.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[dmrconf info codeplug.dfu | less]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  This example will generate a hex dump of the encoded codeplug in the specified DFU file
  <filename>codeplug.dfu</filename>. The result is piped to <command>less</command> for easy 
  reading. The hex dump also prints some information about the file structure as well as
  memory addresses. It also collapses repetitive memory sections (similar to 
  <command>hexdump -C</command>. To this end, this command is a helpful tool for debugging
  the encoding of codeplugs and call-sign DBs.
</para>
</section>

</section>
