<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="confAPRS"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>APRS Systems</title>
</info>

<para>
  The APRS system list specifies the various informations for transmitting your position using analog 
  APRS. As digital channels may use either DMR or analog APRS for position reporting, this list shares 
  a namespace with the GPS system list. That is, the ID must be unique across both lists.
</para>

<informalexample pgwide="1">
  <programlisting><![CDATA[APRS Name                Channel Period Source      Destination Path                   Icon        Message
2    "APRS APAT81"       103     300    DM3MAT-7    APAT81-0    "WIDE1-1WIDE2-1"       "Jogger"    "Y07" 
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  The first column specifies the ID of the APRS positioning system. This must be unique across APRS and DMR 
  position reporting systems. The second column specifies the name of the system as a string. the third 
  column specifies the revert channel. That is, the analog channel the APRS information is transmitted on.
  The 4th column specifies the period with which the position gets reported. The 5th and 6th columns specify 
  the source and destination calls and SSIDs respectively. The 7th column specifies the path string. This is 
  list of calls and SSIDs stored as a string without any separators. The 8th column specifies the map 
  <link xlink:href="http://www.aprs.org/symbols/symbols-new.txt">icon name</link>. The name does not 
  need to match official icon name exactly. The icon is identified as the closes matching icon name with 
  respect to the <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Levenshtein_distance">Levenshtein 
  distance</link> between the given and all icon names. That is, <emphasis>jogger</emphasis> and 
  <emphasis>jogging</emphasis> will select the same icon. Finally, the 9th column specifies a freely 
  selectable text to be send with the position report.
</para>

</section>