<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="confFormat"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
         
<info>
  <title>Table Based Codeplug Format</title>
</info>        

<warning>
  <para>
    This chapter describes the old and deprecated table based <filename>conf</filename> text-file
    format. This format is already incomplete and will remains so. This documentation is maintained
    for the sake of completeness but you should not use that format in future.
  </para> 
  <para>
    <application>qdmr</application> will still be able to import this format but it will not save 
    codeplugs in that format anymore. The new codeplug format is documented in 
    <xref linkend="codeplug"/>.
  </para>
</warning>

<para>
  This configuration file format represents a generic configuration 
  for a wide variety of radios. It is a simple text file containing simple key-value
  definitions like the DMR ID as well as tables like the table of channels, contacts, etc.
</para>

<para>
  The aim of this config format is to be human-readable and writable. This would allow
  users to write config file by hand and share them easily, as well as enable users to modify shared
  configurations using a text editor. To this end, the format must be intuitive and to some
  degree self-documenting.
</para>

<para>
  Within the following sections, I will describe that text format in some detail.
</para>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Line comments</title>
</info>
  
<para>
  To document your configuration, you may use so-called line-comments. These comments start with the
  character <code>#</code> and end at the end-of-line.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting language="ini"><![CDATA[# A comment, everything in this line is ignored
ID: 12345678   # Another comment
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>
</section>


<xi:include href="radiosettings.xml"/>
<xi:include href="contacts.xml"/>
<xi:include href="grouplists.xml"/>
<xi:include href="digitalchannels.xml"/>
<xi:include href="analogchannels.xml"/>
<xi:include href="zones.xml"/>
<xi:include href="scanlists.xml"/>
<xi:include href="gpssystems.xml"/>
<xi:include href="aprssystems.xml"/>
<xi:include href="roaming.xml"/>

</chapter>