<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="confRadioSettings"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>General configuration</title>  
</info>


<para>
  The general configuration settings of some radios can be overly complex with a huge amount of
  options. The vast majority of these settings, however, are useless for ham-radio purposes. Thus
  the possible settings for the general configuration of the radio are reduced to 6 key-value
  pairs.
</para>

<para>
  The DMR ID of cause, is absolutely necessary and specifies your personal DMR number. Keep in
  mind, that you do NOT need to get a unique DMR ID for each radio you own! All your radios can
  share the same DMR ID. The DMR ID is specified using the "ID" keyword as
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting language="ini"><![CDATA[ID: 12345678
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  In rare situations, where you actually need several different radio IDs (e.g., if you use the 
  same radio for HAM and commercial applications), you may specify them as a comma separated list.
  The first ID in the list will be handled as the default ID for the radio. 
</para>

<para>
  The radio name is a string, that the radio may display somewhere on the screen. It does not have
  any effect on the behavior of the radio or gets transmitted. You may set this entry to your
  call-sign. For example:
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[Name: "DM3MAT" 
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  The two intro lines might be shown on the screen of your radio on startup. You may set these
  to any string you like. They are also cosmetic and don't have any effect on the behavior of
  your radio. For example
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[IntroLine1: "Hello"
IntroLine2: "MY0CALL"   
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  The microphone sensitivity/amplification can also be set (on some radios) using the MicLevel
  entry. This entry is also a number between 1 and 10. The larger the level the larger the
  microphone amplification. This value may vary heavily from model to model.
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[MicLevel: 2
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

<para>
  The "Speech" option enables the speech synthesis of the radio if supported. Possible settings
  are "on" and "off".
</para>

<informalexample>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[# Speech-synthesis ('On' or 'Off'):
Speech: Off 
]]></programlisting>
</informalexample>

</section>