<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="reverseEngineering"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

<info>
  <title>Reverse engineering</title>
</info>

<para>
  The majority of the development time needed for <application>qdmr</application>, consists of 
  reverse engineering the codeplug and communication protocols of the radios. Fortunately, many 
  radios share the same communication protocol, in particular those from the same manufacturer.
  But sometimes these protocols are also used by other manufacturers. Even if the protocol is 
  already implemented in <application>qdmr</application>, you may need to reverse engineer the 
  codeplug format. This step has to be performed always, even if a already implemented codeplug
  is reused, you will need to verify that format. Any mistake here, may brick your device.
</para>
<note>
  <para>
    Before you attempt to reverse engineer anything, consider to invest some significant time in 
    research. Reverse engineering is an cumbersome and frequently frustrating task, there is no
    need to waste your valuable time on something, that someone else has already done. Also, 
    consider documenting and publishing your results, so others can find it, even if it is 
    incomplete.
  </para>
</note>
<para>
  In the following sections, I attempt to describe, how I approach reverse engineering the 
  communication protocols and codeplugs. To this end, I hope it might help you in your reverse 
  engineering work. And if you like, you may contribute your work to qdmr.
</para>

<section>
<info><title>Reverse engineering communication protocols</title></info>
<para>
  There is no one ultimate way to successfully reverse engineer a communication protocol. But some
  methods are very common. First, one needs to get some captures of the communication between the 
  manufacturer codeplug programming software (<acronym>CPS</acronym>) and the radio of interest. 
  The majority of theses radios will communicate via USB. Hence, some means are needed to capture
  USB traffic.
</para>
<para>
  There is an application, called <application>Wireshark</application> 
  (<ulink url="https://www.wireshark.org/"/>). This application is usually used to capture and 
  analyze network traffic. It can, however, also capture traffic from USB. How this is done, 
  depends a bit on the operating system you are using. If you want to capture and analyze the 
  communication under <trademark>Windows</trademark>, read the instructions at 
  <ulink url="https://wiki.wireshark.org/CaptureSetup/USB"/>. This makes sense, as you need a 
  windows installation, to run the manufacturer CPS. 
</para>
<para>
  I personally prefer to work under Linux, to this end, I've installed Windows in a virtual 
  machine, but capture the USB traffic under the host Linux system. To do that, the 
  <command>usbmon</command> kernel module must be loaded. If loaded, Wireshark will show USB
  as a capture source.
</para>
<para>
  Once, capturing USB traffic works, connect the radio to the host. You may need to allow the 
  guest system to have access to the USB device. Then fire up the manufacturer CPS, start 
  capturing in Wireshark and start a codeplug read. Stop capturing once the read is complete.
  Save the captured data and restart the capturing. Then write the codeplug back to the device,
  stop the capture and save it in another file.
</para>
<para>
  These files now contain all packets send and received by the PC over USB. In a next step, 
  the packets must be filtered and inspected. To do that, I personally prefer to write short
  Python scripts. The <productname>pyshark</productname> package provides means to read 
  packages from the capture file and access their content. This allows to filter those
  packages to and from the device, that contain the actual payload to and from the device.
</para>
<para>
  Please note, that may radios may misuse some already existing protocols over USB. Some 
  Radioddity and Baofeng devices use the HID specification to transfer data to and from 
  the device. Others may use the DFU specification (TyT, Retevis), mass storage (CSi) or 
  simply serial-over-USB (AnyTone). Irrespective of the underlying specification used to
  send data to the device, the payload of these packages must be extracted.
</para>
<para>
  To do that, use Wireshark to inspect these packages by hand. Search for a packet, that 
  was definitely send to or by the device and note the USB (URB) device address. This is 
  the best way to filter all packets to and from the device.
</para>
<example>
  <title>Some simple example to filter packages by device address and destination/source.</title>
  <programlisting language="python"><![CDATA[
import pyshark

packages = pyshark.FileCapture(FILENAME, include_raw=True, use_json=True)
device_address = '9' # just an example

for package in packages:
  if device_address != package.usb.device_address:
    continue
  if "host" == package.usb.src:
    # From host to device.
  else if "host" == package.usb.dst:
    # From device to host.]]>
  </programlisting>
</example>
<para>
  This example shows how to filter only those packets to and from a specific device and also 
  dispatch depending on the destination and source of the packet. That is, if the packet was 
  send by the host or the device. 
</para>
<para>
  In a next step, the captured payload must be inspected. If the packet contains any additional
  payload data, the <varname>usb.data_length</varname> field will be set. Then, there is a field
  called <varname>usb.capdata_raw</varname>. Unfortunately, that field name contains a dot, so you
  need to access it differently. That is
</para>
<programlisting language="python"><![CDATA[
  # [...] 
  if int(package.usb.data_length):
    data = package["usb.capdata_raw"].value
  # [...]]]>
</programlisting>
<para>
  The extracted data is hex string. Now comes the difficult part. Staring at these packets and 
  making sense of them. Usually, the communication is performed in a strict command-response 
  structure. That is, the host sends a request packet and the device responses with a single 
  packet. This eases the analysis a lot, as the communication is always initiated by the host and
  the association between the request and the response packets are trivial.
</para>

<section>
<title>Identifying the communication structure</title>
<para>
  A typical communication with the device is performed in three steps: First, the 
  radio is identified and brought into a programming mode. Several packets might be needed to 
  perform this task. In that state, the radio usually displays some message on the screen or
  blinks an LED.
</para>
<para>
  The second step consists of the actual codeplug transfer. There, a large 
  amount of packets are send. This step is usually easy to find within the captured packets, as a
  large number of equally sized packets are exchanged. Sometimes, a relatively large amount of 
  data is read or written at once. This can be spotted easily, as basic control commands of 
  the first step are usually pretty short.
</para>
<para>
  Frequently, these packets contain an address field or sequence number used to specify where the 
  codeplug data chunk is written to or read from. These fields are of upmost importance and need to
  be identified. They are, however, easy to spot, as this field is likely constantly increasing, 
  with a fixed increment from packet to packet. 
</para>
<para>
  The final step usually is to reboot the radio or leaving the programming mode. This is commonly 
  performed by a single packet. Sometimes, the device reboots immediately and no response to the 
  command is received by the host. 
</para>
<para>
  Once the protocol structure is identified, that is, the purpose of the single packets is known, 
  the actual work of identifying the packet structure can start. 
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Identifying the packet format</title>
<para>
  The actual packet format will be much harder to reverse engineer. I cannot give any general 
  suggestions on how to figure out the meaning of each byte in a packet. However, I can give you 
  some examples. This might help in reverse engineering new protocols as the structure of the 
  packets will be different, but the concepts remain the same. For example, read and write commands
  must somehow specify an address to read from and write to as well as the amount of data to read 
  or write. This might be helpful
</para>
<para>
  Let us inspect some packets send and received from an AnyTone device.
</para>
<example xml:id="revEngD578">
  <title>Capture of a codeplug read from an AnyTone AT-D578UV</title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[> 50 52 4f 47 52 41 4d                            | PROGRAM
< 51 58 06                                        | QX.

> 02                                              | .
< 49 44 35 37 38 55 56 00 12 56 31 31 30 00 00 06 | ID578UV..V110...

> 52 02 64 00 00 10                               | R.d...
< 57 02 64 00 00 10 fe ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff | W.d.............
| ff ff ff ff ff ff 65 06                         | ......e.

> 52 02 64 00 10 10                               | R.d...
< 57 02 64 00 10 10 ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff | W.d.............
| ff ff ff ff ff ff 76 06                         | ......v.

> 52 02 64 00 20 10                               | R.d. .
< 57 02 64 00 20 10 ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff | W.d. ...........
| ff ff ff ff ff ff 86 06                         | ........

...

> 52 01 64 08 80 10                               | R.d...
< 57 01 64 08 80 10 00 ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff | W.d.............
| ff ff ff ff ff ff ee 06                         | ........

> 52 02 48 02 00 10                               | R.H...
< 57 02 48 02 00 10 01 08 00 00 ff ff ff ff ff ff | W.H.............
| ff ff ff ff ff ff 59 06                         | ......Y.

... ]]></programlisting>
</example>
<para>
  The <xref linkend="revEngD578"/> shows a capture of the data exchanged between the host 
  and an AnyTone AT-D578UV during a codeplug read. Everything starting with <token>&gt;</token> is
  send from the host to the device, while everything starting with <token>&lt;</token> is send by 
  the device to the host.
</para>
<para>
  The first packet send, is the ASCII string <token>PROGRAM</token>. This causes the device to enter
  the programming mode. A message will be shown on the screen of the device. This is then 
  acknowledged by the device with a short message <token>QX</token> followed by a single 
  <token>06h</token> byte. The last byte appears to be weird, but it will always be present on any 
  response from the device. This might be seen as an end-of-packet byte.
</para>
<para>
  The next command send by the host is pretty simple. It consists of a single <token>02h</token> 
  byte. The device responds with a 15 bytes long ID string, identifying the device name and hardware
  version followed by the 06h end-of-packet byte. 
</para>
<para>
  After this, the actual codeplug read appears to start. The host sends a series of equally size 
  commands, each starting with an <token>R</token> followed by 5 bytes of payload. As mentioned 
  above, this payload must contain some sort of memory address and length field, to specify how 
  much to read and from where. To figure that out, one may study subsequent read requests. 
</para>
<para>
  The payloads of the first tree read read requests are 
  <programlisting><![CDATA[02 64 00 00 10
02 64 00 10 10
02 64 00 20 10
]]></programlisting>
  The only difference of these requests is the fourth byte. Hence, one may assume, that this byte is 
  part of the address field. However, we do not know wich bytes are part of the address as well. 
</para>
<para>
  The responses to these requests also contain these bytes as well as 18 more bytes of payload. It is 
  reasonable that the transfer size is a power of two. So the request likely reads 16 bytes from the 
  device. 16 in hex is <token>10h</token>, hence one may assume that the last byte specifies the 
  amount of data to read. Hence we identified the size field as the fifth byte of the read request 
  payload data.
</para>
<para>
  As the address increases by 10h from request to request, one may infer, that the read request
  specifies the address to read from, not the sequence or block number of a read from. As the 
  entire Codeplug will not fit into 256 bytes, the address field must be larger. Even 64kb will 
  be too small, to hold the entire codeplug, the address is likely a 32bit integer. 
</para>
<para>
  This does not need to be true. Some radios will implement special commands to select the memory 
  bank beforehand. Then each 64kB bank can be accessed with a 16bit address. 
</para>
<para>
  To verify our assumption, we will study some read requests, that appear much later and check if 
  the first bytes change as well. And indeed, much later, we observe read request payloads like
  <programlisting><![CDATA[01 64 08 80 10
02 48 02 00 10
]]></programlisting>  
  Obviously, these bytes change too. Consequently, we may assume that the address is stored as a 
  32bit unsigned integer in big-endian byte-order. Finally, we may summarize the read request 
  format as
  <programlisting><![CDATA[+---+---+---+---+---+---+
|'R'| Address       | N |
+---+---+---+---+---+---+]]></programlisting>
Where <token>N</token> is the number of bytes to read.
</para>
<para>
  Now, it is time to study the structure of the read response. As we already reverse engineered the
  read request, the read response is then easy to understand. Each of these responses start with a 
  <token>W</token> char, followed by the same address and length as send by the request. That is
  <programlisting><![CDATA[> 52 02 64 00 00 10
< 57 02 64 00 00 10 fe ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff 65 06]]></programlisting>
  Obviously the 16 byte data read, follows the length byte. The last byte is the common 06h 
  end-of-packet byte, we have already seen. So a single unknown 65h byte is still unknown.
</para>
<para>
  This byte might be some sort of checksum over the payload. Checksums are notoriously difficult to
  figure out. Frequently, common techniques like CRC16 are used. Here, a single checksum byte is 
  used, hence one of the common checksums is unlikely. Now starts some guesswork. We may compare 
  some very similar read responses to get an idea, how this checksum may work. For example
  <programlisting><![CDATA[57 02 64 00 10 10 ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff 76 06
57 02 64 00 20 10 ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff ff 86 06]]></programlisting>
  The only difference between these two responses is one byte in the address, the remaining payload
  is identical. The address also only differs by 10h like the checksum. So one may assume, that the 
  checksum is simply the sum over the payload bytes. Summing all bytes of the latter up to the 
  checksum gets 10ddh. Of cause, this is not the checksum directly. The checksum is a single byte. 
  But the least significant byte of the sum (ddh), however, does not match.
</para>
<para>
  Maybe, the sum is not taken over the entire payload, but over the part that actually matters. That 
  is, the address, length and data fields. This time, the sum is 1086h and this time, the least 
  significant byte (86h) matches the checksum. Now, we can summarize the read response format as
  <programlisting><![CDATA[+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+...+---+---+---+
|'W'| Address       | N | Data (N)  |CRC|06h|
+---+---+---+---+---+---+---+...+---+---+---+]]></programlisting>
  where the CRC is the least significant byte of the sum over the address, length and data payload.
</para>
</section>

</section>
</chapter>