<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<glossary  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
           xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Glossary</title>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Admit Criterion</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>All Call</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        An all-call is a special type of an DMR call to a special number (<emphasis>16777215</emphasis>). 
        All radios are supposed to receive this call irrespective of their particular configuration. This
        call type is usually used in emergency situations or on simplex channels.
      </para>
      <para>
        Unfortunately, the local talk group (number 9) is frequently used on simplex channel although only 
        those radios will receive calls to this talk group if it is in the group list assigned to the 
        simplex channel. To be on the save side, use the all-call for simplex calls.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Automatic Packet Reporting System</glossterm> <acronym>APRS</acronym>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The Automatic Packet Reporting System is a protocol that uses single broadcast frequencies 
        to transmit small amounts of information though a network of repeaters. Usually but not 
        limited to position reports. This allows other services (e.g.,
        <link xlink:href="https://aprs.fi">aprs.fi</link> to display that information on a map. The
        usual APRS frequencies are 144.390 MHz (North America), 144.800 MHz (Europe) and 
        145.175 MHz (Australia).
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Codeplug</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Color Code</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>EchoLink</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        EchoLink is a network of analog FM repeaters that allows to link repeaters within this 
        network temporarily. That is, two FM repeaters that are linked via EchoLink behave like 
        a single repeater irrespective of their location. This network also allows to access
        the repeaters directly though the internet. This is particularly helpful if one cannot 
        reach any repeater.  
      </para>  
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Group Call</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Group List</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Maidenhead Locator</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Private Call</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Revert Channel</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Roaming Zone</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>SSID</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Talkgroup</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Time Slot</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Transmit Contact</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Transmit Timeout</glossterm> <acronym>TOT</acronym>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Specifies the time of continuos transmission, after which the transmission is interrupted 
        automatically. This prevents the accidental blocking of a repeater or talk group by 
        transmitting continuously. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Scan List</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Zone</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
</glossary>