<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<glossary xml:id="glossary"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Glossary</title>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Admit Criterion</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The admit criterion specifies a criterion under which transmissions on a channel are 
        allowed. These criteria can be defined for both, analog and DMR channels. Irrespective of
        the channel type, the admit criteria <quote>always</quote> and <quote>channel free</quote>
        can be selected. The former simply always allows to transmit. The former requires the 
        channel to be free. 
      </para>
      <para>
        For analog channels, usually there is also the criterion <quote>tone</quote>. This 
        criterion would only allow transmissions if the matching CTCSS tone or DCS code has been
        received. For analog repeater operation, the criterion <quote>channel free</quote> should
        not be used as this would prevent any transmissions while the repeater is active.
      </para>
      <para>
        For digital channels, usually there is also the criterion <quote>color code</quote>. This
        criterion would only allow transmissions if the matching color code has been received. To 
        this end, this criterion is similar to the <quote>tone</quote> criterion for analog 
        channels.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>All Call</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        An all-call is a special type of an DMR call to a special number (<emphasis>16777215</emphasis>). 
        All radios are supposed to receive this call irrespective of their particular configuration. This
        call type is usually used in emergency situations or on simplex channels.
      </para>
      <para>
        Unfortunately, the local talk group (number 9) is frequently used on simplex channel although only 
        those radios will receive calls to this talk group if it is in the group list assigned to the 
        simplex channel. To be on the save side, use the all-call for simplex calls.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Automatic Packet Reporting System</glossterm> <acronym>APRS</acronym>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The Automatic Packet Reporting System is a protocol that uses single broadcast frequencies 
        to transmit small amounts of information though a network of repeaters. Usually but not 
        limited to position reports. This allows other services (e.g.,
        <link xlink:href="https://aprs.fi">aprs.fi</link> to display that information on a map. The
        usual APRS frequencies are 144.390 MHz (North America), 144.800 MHz (Europe) and 
        145.175 MHz (Australia).
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Codeplug</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The term <quote>codeplug</quote> is rather loosely defined. Usually it refers to the binary
        representation of the configuration of a radio that is written to the radio to configure it.
        It contains all contacts, channels, zones, settings, etc that form the configuration of the
        radio.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Color Code</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A color code is some additional information attached to each DMR call. It is used to prevent 
        interference between repeaters with overlapping ranges that operate at the same frequencies. 
        In amateur radio, this may only happen in very densely populated areas. It is much more 
        frequent in commercial applications, where a single company may got only a few frequencies 
        assigned but needs much more repeaters to cover a campus reliably.
      </para>
      <para>
        The color code is a number between 0 and 16. A radio or repeater may only react to calls with
        matching color codes. Hence beside the actual input and output frequencies, the color code of
        a repeater must be known to be able to access it.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>DAPNET</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        <acronym>DAPNET</acronym>, short for Decentralized Amateur Paging Network does exactly what
        it says. It is a network of transmitters that transmit pager messages in the UHF band, 
        usually at 439.9875 MHz. As the old pager operated at a frequency near by, they can be 
        modified to operate at that frequency and can therefore be used in amateur radio. 
      </para>
      <para>
        The DAPNET is particularly popular with emergency operators as it allows for an convenient
        and reliable multicast notification.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>DCDM</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Stands for dual capacity direct mode. This allows for two independent connections on a 
        single simplex channel by TDMA. Lacking a single central repeater, one of the 
        participants must act as the so-called <emphasis>leader</emphasis>. This radio then defines
        the clock and thus time slot 1 and 2. All remaining participants must act as so-called 
        <emphasis>follower</emphasis>. They must synchronize to the clock of the 
        <emphasis>leader</emphasis>. This obviously requires that all participants can reach the 
        <emphasis>leader</emphasis> directly.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>EchoLink</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        EchoLink is a network of analog FM repeaters that allows to link repeaters within this 
        network temporarily. That is, two FM repeaters that are linked via EchoLink behave like 
        a single repeater irrespective of their location. This network also allows to access
        the repeaters directly though the internet. This is particularly helpful if one cannot 
        reach any repeater.  
      </para>  
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Group Call</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A group call is simply a call to a talk group. That is, not to a single participant but 
        rather to a group of participants. Every participant that has this talk group in their 
        group list can receive this call. See also <glossterm>Group List</glossterm> and
        <glossterm>Talk Group</glossterm>.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Group List</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A group list is a simple list of talk groups. A group list is then assigned to a channel
        to specify which group calls to receive on that channel. If a talk group is not listed in 
        the group list of a channel, the radio will ignore calls to this talk group on that 
        channel.
      </para>
      <para>
        The DMR network cannot know which talk groups you are interested in. You have to tell your
        radio using group lists.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Maidenhead Locator</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        The Maidenhead locator, also known as <quote>QTH locator</quote> or 
        <quote>IARU locator</quote> is a means for transferring a geo-location over radio. Using a
        so-called grid-square system.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Private Call</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A DMR call to an individual participant. Usually, radios do not receive private calls not
        addressed to the radio. This therefore can be used to talk to a specific HAM over a 
        repeater without disturbing other participants. The repeater however, will be blocked 
        during that time.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Revert Channel</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A revert channel is a designated channel the radio resorts to, to transfer some information
        or the radio switches to, when the PTT is pressed. This is usually used in the context of 
        APRS (i.e., the channel to switch to send the position) or scan lists (i.e., the channel
        the radio will switch to, when the PTT is pressed during the scan).
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Roaming Zone</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A collection of channels usually sharing the same transmit contact. When roaming is enabled
        (and supported by the radio) this list of channels is scanned for a reachable channel once 
        the current repeater gets out-of-range. This way, one can stay in contact with a particular 
        talk group when being mobile.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>SSID</glossterm>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Talk Group</glossterm>
  </glossentry>
  
  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>TDMA</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        See Time Slot.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Time Slot</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Due to the lossy compression of audio data, it is possible to send more than twice the 
        amount of audio data through a single 12.5kHz wide channel that needed. This allows to 
        provide two independent audio streams within a single physical channel. 
      </para>
      <para>
        There are basically two ways to separate these two audio stream. Either by frequency, 
        effectively splitting the single 12.5kHz channel into two 6.25kHz wide ones. Alternatively,
        one can split the channel in <quote>time</quote>. That is, the band width remains 12.5kHz
        but each of the two simultaneous participants sends one after the other. One in time slot 1
        and the other in time slot 2. This is called TDMA and DMR uses this technique to provide 
        two independent audio and data streams within a single physical channel.
      </para>
      <para>
        For this TDMA to work, one participant needs to define the <quote>clock</quote> to specify
        when time slot 1 or 2 happen. This role is usually taken by the repeater but on direct 
        simplex connections, one of the participants might provide that clock. This is then called
        DCDM (Dual-Capacity Direct Mode). This mode, however, makes little sense in amateur radio
        context.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Transmit Contact</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A transmit or default contact can be specified for each DMR channel. Some radios actually 
        require that each channel has an transmit contact. This contact can be any contact you want
        to call whenever the PTT is pressed on that channel. 
      </para>
      <para>
        It, however, possible to answer any received call directly by pressing the PTT button 
        within the so-called hang time, although the call may not match the transmit contact. 
        These hang times can be set within the radio settings, usually for private and group calls
        separately.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is also possible to call any contact by selecting it from the contact list or by 
        entering the contacts DMR ID into the keypad.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Transmit Timeout</glossterm> <acronym>TOT</acronym>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        Specifies the time of continuos transmission, after which the transmission is interrupted 
        automatically. This prevents the accidental blocking of a repeater or talk group by 
        transmitting continuously. 
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Scan List</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        A scan list is just a list of analog and digital channels that one wants to scan. A scan
        list can be associated with each channel. This scan list is then used whenever a scan is
        started on that channel.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>

  <glossentry>
    <glossterm>Zone</glossterm>
    <glossdef>
      <para>
        As there are usually several channels defined per repeater (at least two), the number of 
        defined channels grows rapidly. To organize this large number of channels, zones are used.
        These zones usually collect all relevant channels for a region. That is all (analog and 
        digital) channels associated with the local repeaters. The relevant zone is then selected 
        via the keypad on the radio and only those channels in that zone are then accessible. 
      </para>
      <note>
        <para>
          A defined channel that is not member of any zone is usually not accessible in the radio.
        </para>
      </note>
      <para>
        Some radios allow to specify a different zones for each VFO. Others set a zone globally. 
        In the latter case, the zone consists of two channel lists. One for each VFO.
      </para>
    </glossdef>
  </glossentry>
</glossary>