<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="yamlRadioSettings"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<info>
  <title>Radio settings</title>
</info>         

<para>
  The radio settings section contains all radio-wide settings. For example the microphone level, 
  boot text etc. For now, there aren't many.
</para>

<para>
  As an example, consider the following general settings
</para>

<example pgwide="1">
  <title>General radio-wide settings.</title>
  <programlisting language="yaml"><![CDATA[settings:
  micLevel: 6
  speech: false
  introLine1: qDMR
  introLine2: DM3MAT
  defaultID: id1 
  squelch: 1
  vox: 0
  power: High
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>
  Here, the microphone amplification is set to 6, the speech synthesis is disabled, the two boot
  text lines are set to <quote>qDMR</quote> and <quote>DM3MAT</quote> respectively and the default 
  DMR radio ID is set to <quote>id1</quote>. The latter is the id of a radio ID defined below. 
</para>

<para>
  Also, the radio-wide default squelch, VOX and power level is set. These values can be referenced
  later in channels. Also, some radios do not allow for these settings to be applied on a 
  per-channel basis. For these radios, these values are used. 
</para>

<variablelist>
  <title>Radio-wide Setting Fields</title>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>micLevel</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the microphone amplification. Must be an integer between 1 and 10.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>speech</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Enables/disables the speech synthesis. Some radios can announce the current 
        channel etc. for the visually impaired. To enable that feature (if supported by the radio)
        set this field to <token>true</token>. Must be a boolean value.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>introLine1</token></term>
    <term><token>introLine2</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Sets the two boot text lines (if supported by the radio). These text lines will show up 
        on the boot of the radio. If the radio is set to show a picture during boot, these lines are 
        not shown.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>defaultID</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies which radio ID will be used as the default DMR ID (see 
        <xref linkend="cpRadioIDs"/> below). If none is specified, the first 
        defined DMR radio ID will be used.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>squelch</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the default squelch level. This value may be referenced in channels or 
        represent the radio-wide squelch setting. Any value in [0-10] is valid, where 0 implies 
        an open squelch (if supported by the radio).
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>vox</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the default VOX sensitivity. This value may be referenced in channels or 
        represent the radio-wide VOX sensitivity. Any value in [0-10] is valid here, where 0 
        disables the VOX.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>power</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the default transmit power. This value may be referenced in channels or 
        represent the radio-wide power setting. Possible values are <token>Min</token>, 
        <token>Low</token>, <token>Mid</token>, <token>High</token> and <token>Max</token>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>

  