<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="cpScanLists"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Scan lists</title>
</info>

<para>
  Scan lists are simple lists of channels to scan. A scan list might be associated with a channel.
</para>

<para>
  As an example, consider the following scan list:
</para>

<example pgwide="1">
  <title></title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[scanLists:
  - id: scan1
    name: KW
    channels: [ch4, ch5, ch76, ch77, ch97, ch102, ch68, ch112] 
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>
  This scan list has the ID <emphasis>scan1</emphasis>, the name <emphasis>KW</emphasis> and contains several channels 
  (both analog and digital).
</para>

<variablelist>
  <title>Scan list fields</title>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>id</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specifies the ID of the scan list. This ID can then be used to reference this scan 
        list in <xref linkend="cpChannels"/>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>name</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specifies the name of the scan list. Any string is valid here.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>primary</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specifies the primary priority channel. Usually this channel is scanned very frequently. 
        If set, this must be a reference to a channel. If the tag <token>!selected</token> is used here,
        the channel from which the scan got started is used as the primary priority channel.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>secondary</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specifies the secondary priority channel. Usually this channel is scanned frequently. 
        If set, this must be a reference to a channel. If the tag <token>!selected</token> is used here,
        the channel from which the scan got started is used as the secondary priority channel.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>revert</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Specifies the revert channel. That is, the channel to transmit on irrespective of the 
        current channel being scanned. If set, this must be a reference to a channel. If the tag 
        <token>!selected</token> is used here, the channel from which the scan got started is used 
        as the transmit channel. If omitted the radio will transmit on the currently scanned 
        channel.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>channels</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the list of channels to scan. Must be a list of channel IDs.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
