<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="cpZones"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Zones</title>
</info>

<para>
  The <token>zones</token> element collects all zones defined within the codeplug. It is just a 
  list of zone definitions. Each zone has an ID, name and one or two lists of channels. 
  One for VFO A and one for VFO B. Depending on the radio, a zone will be split automatically into
  two zones if the radio handles separate zones for each VFO. 
</para>  

<para>
  As an example, consider the following zone:
</para>

<example pgwide="1">
  <title>Zone definition</title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[zones:
  - id: zone1
    name: KW
    A: [ch1, ch4, ch5, ch2, ch6, ch11, ch12, ch13, ch15, ch16, ch76, ch77, ch78, ch79]
    B: [ch97, ch101, ch102, ch103, ch68, ch69, ch70, ch71, ch72, ch73, ch74, ch75]
]]></programlisting>
</example>

<para>
  This zone has the name <emphasis>KW</emphasis> and contains two lists of channels. One for each VFO. On radios, 
  where each VFO is assigned a zone individually, this zone will be split into two: <emphasis>KW A</emphasis> and 
  <emphasis>KW B</emphasis> to match the radios configuration. 
</para>

<variablelist>
  <title>Zone fields</title>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>id</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the ID of the zone. For now, there are no codeplug elements that refer to zones.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>name</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the name of the zone. Any string is valid here.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>A</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Specifies the channel list for VFO A. This must be a list of references to channels.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term><token>B</token></term>
    <listitem>
      <para>Optional channel list for VFO B. If present, must be a list of references to channels.</para>
    </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</section>
