<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="intro" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
    Before you start with programming your <acronym>DMR</acronym> radio, 
    <link xlink:href="https://www.dmrfordummies.com/">get familiar</link> with this digital 
    mode. I have also written 
    <link xlink:href="https://dm3mat.darc.de/qdmr/manual/script_de.pdf">a brief introduction into 
    <acronym>DMR</acronym></link> in german. This manual only describes how program your radio using 
    <acronym>qdmr</acronym>, not how <acronym>DMR</acronym> works and what all these weird 
    terms mean.
  </para>
  <para>
    Digital mobile radio (DMR) was not invented for the use in amateur radio. It was rather designed
    to be a radio standard for commercial applications in large companies (e.g., airports etc.).
    Therefore many features of this standard are of no use for ham radio or are even illegal
    (e.g., encryption). This complexity of the standard makes the programming of the radios
    cumbersome.
  </para>
  <para>
    Moreover, the resulting configuration (codeplug) is highly device-dependent. These
    codeplugs cannot be shared between different devices let alone between different vendors. For
    commercial applications, this is not a big problem as a company will most likely buy identical
    radios at once from one company. Thus codeplug can be shared between all radios.
  </para>
  <para>
    For ham radio applications, this incompatibility is a real issue. Since assembling a decent
    codeplug for one region is hard enough, doing the same work all over again for different models
    of different vendors is not manageable.
  </para>
  <para>
    Finally, the typical code-plug programming software (CPS), particularly those for cheap Chinese
    DMR radios, is by no means user-friendly and seldom documented completely. Many options are
    named cryptic and it is not possible to identify which options are necessary for basic DMR
    operation. Moreover, the CPSs provided by the vendors usually only run under Windows.
  </para>
  <para>
    The aim of the <acronym>qdmr</acronym>project is to overcome these shortcomings of typical CPSs. It has a
    reduced feature set only supporting those options necessary of amateur radio usage. It tries
    to be user-friendly by finding repeaters nearby and importing their input and output
    frequencies. Moreover, it stores the final codeplug not in a device-specific binary format but
    in a human-readable text format that is device independent and can therefore be shared across
    multiple device and even across vendors.
  </para>
  <para>
    Finally, I try to keep the application well documented. This manual is part of this effort. It
    is a guide on how a codeplug is set up using <acronym>qdmr</acronym>.
  </para>
</chapter>