<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:id="opengd77Extensions"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
<title>OpenGD77 Codeplug Extensions</title>
<para>
  This chapter documents the extensions and settings specific to radios running the OpenGD77 
  firmware.
</para>
<note>
  <para>
    The OpenGD77 codeplug is a specialization of the GD77 codeplug. Consequently 
    all <link xlink:href="radioddityExtensions">Radioddity extensions</link> are also
    applicable to the OpenGD77 codeplug.
  </para>
</note>

<section xml:id="opengd77Channel">
<title>Channel extension</title>
<para>
  This extension allows to specify some channel settings specific for devices running the 
  OpenGD77 firmware. This extension can be added to any channel, analog and digital.
  For now, this extension only allows to specify the power for the channel in more detail.
</para>
<example>
  <title></title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[channels:
  - digital:
      id: ch1
      name: Example channel 
      # all the other channel settings
      openGD77:
        power: P750mW 
]]></programlisting>
</example>
<para> 
  The OpenGD77 channel extension is a mapping named <token>openGD77</token>. It contains the 
  device specific settings for that channel. 
</para>
<section>
<title>Attributes</title>
<para>
  For now, there is only one attribute specifying the more detailed power settings for the 
  channel.
</para>
<table>
  <thead> <tr><td>Element</td> <td>Description</td></tr> </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><token>power</token></td>
      <td>Specifies the detailed power settings for the channel. This is one of the following 
        strings <token>Global</token>, <token>P50mW</token>, <token>P250mW</token>, <token>P500mW</token>, 
        <token>P750mW</token>, <token>P1W</token>, <token>P2W</token>, <token>P3W</token>, 
        <token>P4W</token>, , <token>P5W</token>, <token>Max</token>. Where <token>Global</token> 
        implies that the global power settings is used and <token>Max</token> the maximal possible 
        power is used (usually 7W on VHF and 5.5W on UHF). This power setting overrides the 
        common channel power setting.</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
        
<section xml:id="opengd77Contact">
<title>DMR contact extension</title>
<para>
  This extensions allows to specify some DMR contact attributes for devices running the OpenGD77 
  firmware. This extension is only applicable to DMR (digital) contacts. 
</para>
<example>
  <title></title>
  <programlisting><![CDATA[contacts:
  - dmr:
    name: Example contact 
    number: 1234567
    openGD77:
      timeSlotOverride: TS1
]]></programlisting>
</example>
<para>
  The OpenGD77 contact extension is a mapping named <token>openGD77</token>. It contains the 
  device specific settings for that DMR contact.
</para>
<section>
<title>Attributes</title>
<table>
  <thead> <tr><td>Element</td> <td>Description</td></tr> </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><token>timeSlotOverride</token></td>
      <td>OpenGD77 allows to override the time slot settings for each channel on the bases of
        the selected transmit contact. If the contact has a time slot override set, this time 
        slot is used instead of the channel time slot. This attribute is either <token>None</token>,
        <token>TS1</token> or <token>TS2</token>. If <token>None</token> is set, the channel time slot 
        will not be overridden.
      </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>