<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiAPRS"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Setup GPS/APRS Position Reporting</title>
</info>

<para>
  The <guilabel>GPS/APRS</guilabel> tab allows to specify several so-called positioning systems. A 
  positioning system is a collection of settings on how GPS information is send to 
  <glossterm>APRS</glossterm> network. 
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-positioning.png" width="13cm" align="center"/>></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the GPS or APRS settings.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The list GPS/APRS systems.</title> 
</screenshot>

<section>
<info>
  <title>Edit/Create GPS Systems</title>
</info> 

<para>
  Double-clicking a GPS system or clicking on the <guibutton>Add GPS System</guibutton> button 
  will open the GPS system edit dialog. 
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-gps.png" width="5cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The digital APRS editing dialog.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  This dialog allows to specify how the GPS information is send through the DMR network. That is
  the <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field specifies the name of the GPS system. The 
  <guilabel>Destination</guilabel> field specifies the private-call contact, the information is 
  send to. For example 262999 in the Brandmeister network. The <guilabel>Update Period</guilabel>
  specifies the period in which the current GPS information is send to the contact. The 
  <glossterm>Revert Channel</glossterm> specifies to which channel the radio should switch to, 
  to send the position information. This should always be <guilabel>Selected</guilabel>. That is,
  the radio will always send the information on the currently selected channel. 
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the GPS system. 
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Edit/Create APRS System</title>
</info>

<para>
  Double-clicking an APRS system or clicking on the <guibutton>Add APRS System</guibutton> button 
  will open the <glossterm>APRS</glossterm> system dialog. 
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-aprs.png" width="5cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the edit APRS dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The analog APRS editing dialog.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  This dialog allows to specify how the GPS information is send through the APRS network. That is
  the <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field specifies the name of the APRS system. The 
  <guilabel>Channel</guilabel> field specifies on which channel the APRS information should be 
  send. This must be an analog channel with one of the typical 
  <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Automatic_Packet_Reporting_System#Technical_information"
     >APRS frequencies</link>. The <guilabel>Source</guilabel> field specifies your call and the 
  source <glossterm>SSID</glossterm>, while the <guilabel>Destination</guilabel> field specifies the destination call and
  SSID. Path is an optional string containing the APRS path for the packet. The 
  <guilabel>Icon</guilabel> combo-box allows to select an icon for the packets. These icons are 
  then shown on <link xlink:href="https://aprs.fi">APRS maps</link>. The 
  <guilabel>Update Period</guilabel> specifies how frequently an APRS packet should be send. 
  Finally, the <guilabel>Message</guilabel> field allows to  set an optional text message for the 
  packet. 
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the APRS system. 
</para>
</section>

</section>

  