<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiChannels"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Creating Channels</title>
</info>

<para>
  Creating the list of channels for the DMR radio is the most cumbersome task. Remember, each
  repeater has two time-slots with possibly multiple talk-groups assigned to each time slot. For
  the sake of convenience, it is reasonable to define a channel for each talk-group you are
  interested in, for each time-slot on every repeater. Thus, instead of a single channel per
  analog repeater, you will likely define at least 3-4 channels per DMR repeater. 
</para>

<para>
  To ease the burden of creating a lot of channels, <application>qdmr</application> implements some
  features that should help you in creating these channel. One feature is the automatic retrieval 
  of repeater input and output frequencies from
  <link xlink:href="https://repeatermap.de">repeatermap.de</link>. This is a world-wide map
  of ham-radio repeaters.
</para>

<tip>
  <para>
    When you enter your locator into the settings dialog (see <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), 
    <application>qdmr</application> will provide you with a list of nearby repeater and fill in the
    input and output frequencies. This feature works for both, analog and DMR repeaters. 
  </para>  
</tip>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-channels.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the list of channels.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>List of channels.</title>
</screenshot>

<para> 
  The <guilabel>Channels</guilabel> tab shows the list of all defined channels, irrespective of
  whether they are analog or digital (DMR) channels. You may add an analog or digital channel by 
  clicking on the <guibutton>Add Analog Channel</guibutton> or 
  <guibutton>Add Digital Channel</guibutton> button on the bottom, respectively. 
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Clone Channel</guilabel> button allows for cloning of a selected channel. This 
  enables one to create a set of channels that differ only in the default transmit contact but 
  share the same remaining settings.
</para>

<para>
  You can also delete a channel, by selecting that channel in the list and clicking on the
  <guibutton>Delete Channel</guibutton> button at the bottom. You may move a channel up or down the
  list by selecting that channel and clicking on the <guibutton>arrow-up</guibutton> or 
  <guibutton>-down</guibutton> button to the right, respectively. Finally you can edit a channel by 
  double-clicking it in the list. 
</para>

<tip>
  <para>
    The number of channels usually grow fast and it becomes hard to find channels within the list. 
    To search the list for any channel name or frequency, just hit <accel>Ctrl+F</accel> to open a 
    search box. This search feature is present in all lists. The channel list, however, is likely 
    the largest.
  </para>  
</tip>


<section xml:id="guiDigitalChannelDialog">
<info>
  <title>Edit digital channels</title>
</info>

<para>
  When you double-click on a digital channel or click on the <guibutton>Add Digital 
  Channel</guibutton> button, the digital channel editor dialog will be shown. This dialog allows 
  you to edit or create digital channels.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-digital-channel.png" width="7cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the digital channel editor dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The digital channel editor.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The dialog is limited to the DMR-channel settings that are relevant for amateur radio. Thus, it
  is much smaller that the typical dialogs to edit DMR channels in commercial CPSs.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Name</guilabel>, <guilabel>Rx</guilabel> and <guilabel>Tx Frequency</guilabel> 
  fields contain the chosen name of the channel as well as the transmit and receive frequencies. 
  The latter can be set automatically by using the repeater auto-completion feature: Start to enter
  the call-sign of a repeater. A list of matching nearby repeaters is shown. Select a repeater 
  from this list and the RX/TX frequencies will be set using the information from
  <link xlink:href="https://repeatermap.de">repeatermap.de</link>. For simplex-channels RX
  and TX frequencies must be identical.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Power</guilabel> setting specifies the power used on that channel. For a nearby 
  repeater, you may reduce the power. If you check the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> box, the 
  global power setting will be used. See <xref linkend="guiRadioSettings"/> above.
</para>

<para>
  <guilabel>Tx Timeout</guilabel> (<glossterm>TOT</glossterm>)
  specifies the transmit timeout in seconds. This limits the continuous transmission time to this 
  period. A value of <guilabel>Off</guilabel> disables the timeout. If you check the 
  <guilabel>Default</guilabel> box, the global TOT setting will be used. See 
  <xref linkend="guiRadioSettings"/> above.
</para>

<para>
  <guilabel>VOX Level</guilabel> specifies the sensitivity of the <glossterm>VOX</glossterm>
  for this channel. If <guilabel>OFF</guilabel> is selected, the VOX is disabled for this channel.
  If you check the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> box, the global VOX setting will be used. See 
  <xref linkend="guiRadioSettings"/> above.
</para>
<para>
  Checking <guilabel>Rx Only</guilabel> will disable transmission on this channel. 
</para>

<para>
  <glossterm>Scan List</glossterm> allows to specify the 
  scan list associated with this channel. If a scan is started on this channel, this scan list will 
  be used. Each channel may have a different scan list.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>DMR ID</guilabel> field allows to select the Radio DMR ID for this channel. Some 
  radios allow to program several DMR IDs to be used with one radio. This option makes not sense
  for HAM-radio usage. However, if you use the same radio for HAM as well as commercial 
  applications, you may need to set your HAM DMR ID for HAM-radio channels and your commercial ID
  on commercial channels.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Tx Admit</guilabel> field specifies the <glossterm>Admit Criterion</glossterm>,
  under which you are allowed to transmit on the channel. For DMR repeater channels this 
  should be set to <guilabel>Color Code</guilabel>. This means that you may only transmit if the 
  radio received the correct color code of the repeater before. On simplex channels 
  <guilabel>Channel Free</guilabel> should be chosen and thus the radio will only transmit on 
  the channel if the channel is free.
</para>

<para>
  The <glossterm>Color Code</glossterm> specifies the color code of the repeater. For simplex 
  channels, this should be set to 1. For repeater channels, this must match the color code of 
  the repeater.
</para>

<para>
  The <glossterm>Time Slot</glossterm> specifies the time-slot  of the repeater for this channel. 
  All repeaters have two time slots but different talk groups might be associated with each time 
  slot. You may need to consult the webpage of the repeater. In the <glossterm>Brandmeister 
    network</glossterm>, usually the time-slot 2 is for local/regional communication while 
  time-slot 1 is for <quote>DX</quote>.
</para>

<para>
  The <glossterm>Group List</glossterm> specifies the list of group-calls you want to receive on 
  this channel. See <xref linkend="guiGroupLists"/> above for details.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Tx Contact</guilabel> specifies the default <glossterm>Transmit Contact</glossterm> 
  you want to call on this channel when pressing the PTT button. 
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Positioning System</guilabel> (DMR ARPS) specifies how you location information is 
  send over this channel (selecting <guilabel>None</guilabel> disables GPS for this channel). Please 
  note, that this setting is ignored for radios without GPS.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Roaming</guilabel> allows to associate a roaming zone (see <xref linkend="guiRoaming"/> 
  below) with this channel. If the radios has the roaming feature, this zone is then used to search
  for a another channel of another repeater that is reachable once this repeater get out-of-range.
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the channel. 
</para>
</section>


<section xml:id="guiAnalogChannelDialog">
<info>
  <title>Edit analog channels</title>
</info>

<para>
  When you double-click on an analog channel or click on the <guibutton>Add Analog 
  Channel</guibutton> button, the analog-channel-editor dialog will be shown. This dialog allows 
  for editing or creating analog (FM) channels.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-analog-channel.png" width="7cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the analog channel editor dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The analog channel editor.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The left column of field are identical to the digital channel dialog, that is 
  <guilabel>Name</guilabel>, <guilabel>Rx</guilabel> and <guilabel>Tx Frequency</guilabel>, 
  <guilabel>Power</guilabel>, <guilabel>Tx Timeout</guilabel>, <guilabel>VOX Level</guilabel> 
  <guilabel>Rx Only</guilabel> and <guilabel>Scan List</guilabel>.
</para>

<para>
  Like for digital channels, analog channels may also have an <guilabel>Tx Admit</guilabel> 
  criterion. Possible options are <guilabel>Always</guilabel>, <guilabel>Channel Free</guilabel> 
  and <guilabel>Tone</guilabel>. For FM repeaters the <guilabel>Always</guilabel> option should be 
  chosen to allow for a quick turn-around in a QSO. For simplex channels <guilabel>Channel 
  Free</guilabel> should be chosen, as it only allows to transmit when the simplex channel is free.
  Selecting <guilabel>Channel Free</guilabel> on repeater channels, would prevent transmission while
  the repeater is active although the last transmission already ended.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Squelch</guilabel> field specifies the squelch threshold. If 
  <guilabel>Open</guilabel> is selected, the squelch is disabled. If <guilabel>Default</guilabel>
  is enabled, the global squelch level is used. See <xref linkend="guiRadioSettings"/> above.
</para>

<para>
  <guilabel>Rx</guilabel> and <guilabel>Tx Tone</guilabel> specify the 
  <glossterm>CTCSS</glossterm>/<glossterm>DCS</glossterm>
  tones for this channel/repeater. The <guilabel>Rx Tone</guilabel> specifies the sub-tone that is 
  needed to open the squelch. The <guilabel>Tx Tone</guilabel> specifies the tone that gets 
  transmitted (e.g., to open the repeater).
</para>

<para>
  <guilabel>Bandwidth</guilabel> specifies the band-width of the transmission. Possible 
  values are 12.5kHz (<guilabel>Narrow</guilabel>) or 25kHz (<guilabel>Wide</guilabel>).
</para>

<para>
  <guilabel>APRS</guilabel> allows to specify an APRS system to be used on this channel. If the 
  radio supports analog APRS, your position will be send using the frequency, destination and path
  specified in this APRS system. If <guilabel>None</guilabel> is selected, APRS is disabled for
  this channel. If your radio does not support APRS, this setting is ignored.
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the channel. 
</para>
</section>

</section>

  