<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiContacts"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Creating Contacts</title>
</info>

<para>
  The second tab is the <guilabel>Contact List</guilabel>. Here all DMR contacts are defined, 
  irrespective of their type. It is not only possible to define digital DMR contacts (i.e., 
  private, group and all calls) but also DTMF contact (and in future two-tone, five-tone contacts
  too). This eases the control of the <glossterm>EchoLink</glossterm> features of repeaters.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-contacts.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the contact list tab.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The contact list.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  You may add a contact by clicking on the <guibutton>Add Contact</guibutton> button at the bottom. 
  You can also delete a contact by selecting the contact in the list and clicking on the 
  <guibutton>Delete Contact</guibutton> button at the bottom. You may also reorder the contacts by 
  selecting a contact in the list and use the <guibutton>arrow-up</guibutton> and 
  <guibutton>arrow-down</guibutton> buttons on the left to move the contact up and
  down the list, respectively.
</para>

<para>
  When you create a code-plug, the contact list should contain all talk groups and reflectors you
  are interested in as well as a so-called <glossterm>All Call</glossterm> contact to the number
  <emphasis>16777215</emphasis>. Additionally you may add private calls to several operators you 
  know as well as some <emphasis>service numbers</emphasis>.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-contact.png" width="3cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot new/edit contact dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The new/edit contact dialog.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  When you click on the <guibutton>Add Contact</guibutton> button or when you double-click a 
  contact entry in the list, the <guilabel>Edit Contact</guilabel> dialog will appear. The first 
  drop-down box allows to choose the type of the call. The possible options are <glossterm>Private 
  Call</glossterm>, <glossterm>Group Call</glossterm> and <glossterm>All Call</glossterm>. The second 
  entry is the name of the contact. Here any text can be entered. The third entry is the number of
  the contact. This entry gets disabled when <glossterm>All Call</glossterm> is selected as the 
  call-type. Finally, if the last option <guilabel>Rx Tone</guilabel> is enabled, you will hear a 
  ring-tone whenever this contact calls you.
</para>

<tip>
  <para>
    <application>qdmr</application> tries to download the current list of all registered user DMR-ids.
    The contact dialog will use this information (once downloaded) to resolve call-signs to DMR ids.
    Just start entering the call-sign into the name field and matching call-signs are shown. The same
    holds true for Brandmeister <glossterm>Talkgroup</glossterm> names.
  </para>
</tip>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the GPS system. 
</para>

</section>
