<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiGroupLists"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Assembling Group Lists</title>
</info>

<para>
  <emphasis>RX group lists</emphasis> or simply 
  <glossterm>Group Lists</glossterm>s are just lists of <glossterm>Group Call</glossterm>s you may wish 
  to receive on a channel. Of cause, you may want to receive calls to multiple talk groups on one 
  channel, hence you have to create these lists of talk groups beforehand. 
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-rx-groups.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the RX group lists.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The list of group lists.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Group Lists</guilabel> tab is just a simple list of all group lists you created. You 
  may add a group list by clicking on the <guibutton>Add RX Group</guibutton> button at the bottom.
  You can delete a group list by seleting it in the list and clicking on the 
  <guibutton>Delete RX Group</guibutton> button there. You can also edit a RX group list by 
  double-clicking on that group in the list.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-rx-groups.png" width="5cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the group list edit dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The group list dialog.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  When creating a new group list or when editing one, the <guilabel>Edit Group 
  List</guilabel> dialog will open. Within this dialog, you can change the name of the group at the
  top. In the center of the dialog, you will find the list of group calls of this group list. You 
  can add group call to the list by clicking on the <guibutton>Add Contact</guibutton> button on 
  the bottom. You can also remove contacts from the list by selecting the contact and clicking on the 
  <guibutton>Remove Contact</guibutton> button. When you are done editing the group list, click on 
  the <guibutton>Ok</guibutton> button. The <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton> button will discard all 
  changes and closes the dialog.
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the GPS system. 
</para>
</section>
  