<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiRadioSettings"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>General configuration</title>
</info>

<para>
  The figure below shows the <guilabel>General Configuration</guilabel> tab of 
  <application>qdmr</application>. This tab is divided into 4 sections: 
  <guilabel>DMR Radio ID</guilabel>, <guilabel>Boot Settings</guilabel>, 
  <guilabel>Audio Settings</guilabel> and <guilabel>Channel Default Values</guilabel>. 
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the general configuration like the DMR ID and the radio name.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>General settings tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The general configuration of your radio is the simplest step: You only need to  enter your
  DMR ID and your radio name. The latter is usually just your call sign. If you do not have a DMR
  ID yet, you can request one at 
  <link xlink:href="https://register.ham-digital.org/">ham-digital.org</link>.
</para>

<note>
  <para>
    You will always need only <emphasis>one</emphasis> DMR ID, even if you have several radios. The
    DMR network is able to handle multiple endpoints with the same ID. Never request more than one 
    ID, they are a limited resource.
  </para>
</note>

<para>
  In the rare case, where you actually need more than one DMR ID, for example if you the same 
  radio from HAM as well as commercial applications, you may add your additional DMR IDs using
  the <guilabel>Radio IDs</guilabel> tab. This tab is usually hidden and can be accessed by 
  enabling <guibutton>Show commercial features</guibutton> in the application settings (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/> below).
</para>

<para>
  Within the <guilabel>Boot Settings</guilabel>, the <guilabel>Intro Line 1</guilabel> &amp; 
  <guilabel>2</guilabel> specify the text that some radios show on startup. You may enter any text
  here. Some radios show an image during boot. For those radios, these settings have no effect.
</para>

<para>
  Within the <guilabel>Audio Settings</guilabel>, the <guilabel>MIC amp.</guilabel> option specifies 
  the microphone amplification (if supported by the radio). This must be a value between 1 and 10, 
  where 1 is the smallest amplification and 10 the loudest.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Speech Synthesis</guilabel> option allows for enabling speech synthesis by the 
  radio. Some radios support speech synthesis to help visually impaired 
  operators to handle the radio and navigate its menus. If this option is checked, the speech-synthesis 
  will be enabled if the radio supports this feature.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Channel Default Values</guilabel> block allows to specify some default values that can 
  be referenced by channels (see <xref linkend="guiChannels"/> below). This serves two use cases. First, it 
  allows to set some channel properties for all channels that reference these values at once. More 
  importantly, however, some radios do not allow to set these options on a per-channel basis. For those
  radios, these values are used for all channels.
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), an additional block labeled <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel> 
  is shown at the right side. This view allows to add, remove and edit device specific radio 
  settings. All device specific settings are handled and displayed in the same way. See 
  <xref linkend="guiExtensions"/> for some description of this process.
</para>
</section>
  
  