<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiRadioSettings"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>General configuration</title>
</info>

<para>
  The figure below shows the <guilabel>General Configuration</guilabel> tab of 
  <application>qdmr</application>. This tab is divided into Five subtabs:
  <guilabel>Boot Settings</guilabel>, <guilabel>Audio Settings</guilabel>,
  <guilabel>Tone Settings</guilabel>, <guilabel>Channel Default Values</guilabel>
  and <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel>.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the general configuration tab showing the boot settings.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>General settings tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<section>
<info><title>Boot settings</title></info>
<para>
  Within the <guilabel>Boot Settings</guilabel>, the <guilabel>Intro Line 1</guilabel> &amp; 
  <guilabel>2</guilabel> specify the text that some radios show on startup. You may enter any text
  here. Some radios show an image during boot. For those radios, these settings have no effect.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info><title>Audio Settings</title></info>
<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings-audio.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the audio settings.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>Audio settings tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  Within the <guilabel>Audio Settings</guilabel>, the <guilabel>Default Microphone Amplification</guilabel> specifies
  (by default) the common mic gain for all modes. This must be a value between 1 and 10, where 1 is the smallest
  amplification and 10 the loudest. A separate <guilabel>FM Microphone Amplification</guilabel> can be specified below.
  If <guilabel>Default</guilabel> is selected, the default microphone gain is used instead.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Default Squelch</guilabel> specifies the common squelch level for all modes. This must either be
  <guilabel>Open</guilabel> or a value between 1 and 10. The larger the value, the stronger the station must be to open
  the squelch. A squelch level is usually only relevant for FM channels. Some radios allow to set a separate DMR squelch
  level. This can be done with the <guilabel>DMR Squelch</guilabel> field. If <guilabel>Default</guilabel> is checked,
  the default (FM) squelch is used.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>VOX Sensitivity</guilabel> field specifies the sensitivity of the VOX (voice-operated-switch). If set
  to <guilabel>Off</guilabel>, the VOX is disabled. Otherwise, a value between 1 and 10 must be selected. The larger the
  value, the louder you have to talk into the radio, to trigger the VOX. There is also <guilabel>VOX Delay</guilabel>
  field, specifying a delay before the VOX is triggered. This can be used to avoid unintentional transmission of short
  loud bursts, for example in some working environments.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Maximum Speaker</guilabel> and <guilabel>Maximum Headphone Volumes</guilabel> allow for limiting the
  loudness the speaker or headphone. This can be used to adapt the range of volume knob on the radio to the current
  working environment.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Speech Synthesis</guilabel> option allows for enabling speech synthesis by the 
  radio. Some radios support speech synthesis to help visually impaired 
  operators to handle the radio and navigate its menus. If this option is checked, the speech-synthesis 
  will be enabled if the radio supports this feature.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info><title>Tone Settings</title></info>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings-tone.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the tone settings.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>Tone settings tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The tone settings control some of the sounds generated by the radio. Especially, some radios allow to disable all
  sounds globally. Or to enable/disable or set the volume of the key tones.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>SMS tone</guilabel>, <guilabel>Ringtone</guilabel> and <guilabel>Talk permit</guilabel>  fields allow to
  enable/disable tones sounding, when an SMS, a private all is received or if it is allowed to transmit on the currently
  active channel according to the admit criterion set for that channel. The SMS and private call tones can only be
  enabled or disabled globally, while the talk-permit tone can be enabled on a by-channel-type basis. To enable/disable
  the tone for channel types, click on the pen icon.
</para>

<para>
  The remaining tone-settings concern the boot, call-start, call-end, channel-idle and call-reset melodies. These can
  either be enabled/disabled globally (e.g., boot and call-reset melodies) or enabled for channel types individually.
  Again, click on the pen button to select the channel types. Some radios allow for programming custom melodies for
  these tones. These melodies can be specified in LilyPond format and speed in BPM (beats per minute). The play-button
  on the right plays the specified melody.
</para>

<para>
  <application>qdmr</application> uses a simplified LilyPond format. It consists of a simple, white-space separated
  list of notes and pauses. The general format is
</para>
<para><token>Name</token><token>[Length]</token><token>[Ocave]</token><token>[.]</token></para>
<para>
  Name must be a note name (i.e., <token>c</token>, <token>cis</token>, <token>d</token>, <token>dis</token>,
  <token>e</token>, <token>f</token>, <token>fis</token>, <token>g</token>, <token>gis</token>, <token>a</token>,
  <token>ais</token> or <token>b</token>) or <token>r</token> for a pause (rest).
</para>

<para>
  The length specifies the length of the note or pause. It must be one of <token>1</token>, <token>2</token>,
  <token>4</token>, <token>8</token>, <token>16</token> or <token>32</token>, specifying a whole, half, quarter, ...
  note. Adding a dot (<token>.</token>) to the end of the note extends it by half of its length. I.e. <token>a4.</token>
  will be 3/8th long. The length can also be omitted. In this case, the length of the previous not is re-used.
  Consequently, the first note need an explicit length.
</para>

<para>
  Finally, by adding one or more <token>'</token> the octave can be increased, while adding one or more <token>,</token>
  the octave of a note can be decreased. It is not possible to specify the octave of the entire melody.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info><title>Channel Default Values</title></info>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings-defaults.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the channel default settings.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>Channel default settings tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Channel Default Values</guilabel> block allows to specify some default values that can 
  be referenced by channels (see <xref linkend="guiChannels"/> below). This serves two use cases. First, it 
  allows to set some channel properties for all channels that reference these values at once. More 
  importantly, however, some radios do not allow to set these options on a per-channel basis. For those
  radios, these values are used for all channels.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info><title>Extensions</title></info>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-general-settings-extensions.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the settings extensions.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>Settings extensions tab.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  Finally, the tab labeled <guilabel>Extensions</guilabel> contains extensions. This view allows to add, remove and edit
  device specific radio settings. All device specific settings are handled and displayed in the same way. See
  <xref linkend="guiExtensions"/> for some description of this process.
</para>
</section>

</section>
  
  