<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiScanLists"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Assembling Scan Lists</title>
</info>

<para>
  Scan lists are simple lists of channels that are scanned sequentially, when scanning is started. A
  <glossterm>ScanList</glossterm> may be associated with an analog or digital channel (see 
  <xref linkend="guiChannels"/>).
</para>

<note>
  <para> 
    For many radios, you need to associate a scan list with a channel (see 
    <xref linkend="guiChannels"/> above) in the analog or digital channel edit dialog. This determines 
    which scan list is used, when a scan is started on a particular channel.
  </para>
</note>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-scan-lists.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the list of scan lists.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The list of scan lists.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  A new scan list can be created by clicking on the <guibutton>Add Scan List</guibutton> button. A 
  scan list can be deleted by selecting the scan list and clicking on the <guibutton>Delete Scan 
  List</guibutton> button. The order of the scan list can be changed by selecting a list and moving 
  it up/down using the <guibutton>up</guibutton> and <guibutton>down</guibutton> buttons on the 
  right.
</para>

<para>
  Double-clicking on a scan list or clicking the <guibutton>Add Scan List</guibutton> button will 
  open the scan-list edit-dialog. This dialog allows to alter/assemble the scan list by adding, 
  removing or reordering the channels in the scan list.
</para>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Edit Scan Lists</title>
</info>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-scanlist.png" width="5cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the edit scan-list dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The scan-list editor.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  By double-clicking an existing scan list or clicking on the <guibutton>Add Scan 
  List</guibutton> button, the scan-list dialog opens. The <guilabel>Name</guilabel> field allows 
  to specify the name of the scan list.
</para>

<para>
  The optional <guilabel>Primary</guilabel> and <guilabel>Secondary Channel</guilabel> fields allow
  to specify channels that are visited more frequently. The <guilabel>Primary Channel</guilabel> will
  be visited 50% of the time. That is, after a channel of the scan list was visited, the primary 
  channel is visited again, and after that, the next channel from the scan list is visited. In the end,
  the primary channel is scanned half of the time. The secondary channel is similar but gets visited only
  25% of the time. The drop down list allows to select none, any channel or the <guilabel>Selected</guilabel> 
  channel. The latter refers to the channel, the scan started on. 
</para>

<para>
  The optional <guilabel>Transmit Channel</guilabel> or <glossterm>Revert Channel</glossterm> specifies 
  the channel to transmit on during a scan. Here none, any channel, the selected channel and also the 
  <guilabel>Last</guilabel> channel can be chosen. The <guilabel>Last</guilabel> channel refers to 
  the last active channel on the scan list. This allows to answer a heard call during a scan.
</para>

<para>
  Channels can be added to the scan list by clicking on the <guibutton>Add Channel</guibutton> 
  button at the bottom. Similarly, channels can be removed by selecting them and clicking on the 
  <guibutton>Remove Channel</guibutton> button. Like for all other lists, the channels can be moved 
  around within the list by selecting channels and using the <guibutton>up</guibutton> and 
  <guibutton>down</guibutton> buttons to the right.
</para>

<para>
  If <guilabel>Show Commercial Features</guilabel> is enabled in the settings dialog (see 
  <xref linkend="guiSettingsDialog"/>), a tab bar is shown at the top. There you can also access
  the device specific settings for the scan list. 
</para>
</section>

</section>
