<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiSettingsDialog"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" >


<info>
  <title>Application Settings Dialog</title>
</info>

<para>
  The application settings dialog controls some of the behavior of <application>qdmr</application>.
  The dialog is divided into 4 sections: <guilabel>Location</guilabel>, <guilabel>Radio 
    Programming</guilabel>, <guilabel>Call-Sign DB</guilabel> and <guilabel>Commercial</guilabel>.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-settings-dialog.png" width="5cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen shot of the application settings dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  <title>The settings dialog</title>
</screenshot>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Location settings</title>
</info>

<para>
  The first section concerns the location of the user. You may enter your <glossterm>Maidenhead 
  Locator</glossterm> here or you may enable <guilabel>System location</guilabel>. The latter tries
  to obtain the current location from the operating system. This information is then used in the 
  channel editors (see <xref linkend="guiChannels"/>) to provide auto-completion for repeaters 
  nearby.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Radio programming settings</title>
</info>

<para>
  The second section controls the programming of the radio and how codeplugs are assembled. The 
  first option <guilabel>Update codeplug</guilabel> specifies whether a codeplug is generated from
  scratch or whether the codeplug currently programmed on the radio gets updated. 
  <application>qdmr</application> does not implement all settings possible for all radios, 
  consequently <guilabel>Update codeplug</guilabel> should be choses to maintain all settings 
  of the radio that are not touched by <application>qdmr</application>.
</para>

<para>
  For some radios, the GPS and roaming functionality must be enabled explicitly. The 
  <guilabel>Auto-enable GPS</guilabel> and <guilabel>Auto-enable roaming</guilabel> options
  can be used to automatically enable GPS or roaming. If selected, whenever any channel has a
  GPS/APRS system or a roaming zone associated with it, the GPS and/or roaming gets enabled 
  globally.
</para>

<para>
  As described in <xref linkend="guiProgram"/>, the upload of a codeplug will be paused 
  if some verification warnings are issued. The <guilabel>Ignore verification warnings</guilabel>
  option allows to continue silently even in the presence of verification warnings. The may be 
  needed for some radios with some rather short communication timeout. The radio may reset the 
  connection to the computer while the warnings are shown. To prevent this, this option might be 
  used.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Ignore frequency limits</guilabel> option does exactly what it says. Usually, 
  programming a channel outside of the radios frequency range would issue an error. However, many
  radios are able to receive and even transmit outside of the frequency rangs specified by the 
  manufacturer. But be aware, that transmitting outside the declared frequency range may destroy 
  the radio!
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Call-sign DB settings</title>
</info>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Call-Sign DB</guilabel> section collects options that control the automatic 
  curation of the call-sign DB. Many radios allow to write a large database of call-signs 
  and DMR IDs to the radio. These DBs are then used to resolve DMR IDs to call-signs, names
  etc. and display them. 
</para>

<para>
  Usually, curating these databases is a cumbersome task. <application>qdmr</application> tries to
  automate this taks. Usually, <application>qdmr</application> will select as many call-signs from
  the global database it can fit into the radio. Although modern radios will provide a huge amount
  memory, not all registered IDs can be programmed. In these (all) cases, 
  <application>qdmr</application> will select only the <emphasis>closest</emphasis> IDs to your
  DMR ID (default Radio DMR ID, see <xref linkend="guiRadioSettings"/>). The DMR IDs are compared by 
  the longest matching prefix. This makes sense as DMR IDs are not random. They share the same 
  prefix for countries and regions. This way, <application>qdmr</application> will first select all
  IDs from the same region followed by all IDs from the same country etc. Of cause, there is no 
  rule without any exceptions. Some countries have several prefixes assigned. 
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Limit number of DB entries</guilabel> option and <guilabel>Number of DB 
    entries</guilabel> field allow to limit the number of DB entries written to the device. If 
  the <guilabel>Limit number of DB entries</guilabel> option is disabled, as many entries are 
  written to the deivce as it can hold.
</para>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Select using my DMR ID</guilabel> option and the <guilabel>Select using 
    prefixes</guilabel> field can be used to control the selection of entries. If the
  <guilabel>Select using my DMR ID</guilabel> option is enabled, the aforementioned algorithm is 
  used to select the entries. If this option is disabled, a list of prefixed must be specified in
  the <guilabel>Select using prefixes</guilabel> field. Then the DMR IDs closest to these prefixes
  are used to assemble the final call-sign DB.
</para>
</section>


<section>
<info>
  <title>Commercial feature settings</title>
</info>

<para>
  DMR originated as a standard for commercial radios. Consequently, there are many features that 
  are not relevant or even illegal for ham-radio use (e.g., encryption). However, some operators 
  use their handhelds for both ham-radio and commercial applications. Consequently, 
  <application>qdmr</application> cannot ignore commercial features. It can, however, hide them.
  Enabling the <guilabel>Show commercial features</guilabel> options will show these features.
</para>

<para>
  For now, there are not may commercial features supported by <application>qdmr</application>. 
  Therefore not much is hidden except for the ability to define several DMR radio IDs and the 
  device specific settings.
</para>
</section>
</section>
  