<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<section xml:id="guiZones"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

<info>
  <title>Assembling Zones</title>
</info>

<para>
  You may programm a myriad of different channels for you radio. To organize them in handy chunks,
  zones are used. That is, a zone is just a named list of channels that are relevant for a
  particular area or a particular situation.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-zones.png" width="13cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The list of zones.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  The <guilabel>Zones</guilabel> just lists all defined zones. You may add a 
  <glossterm>Zone</glossterm> using the <guibutton>Add Zone</guibutton> button or you may delete 
  one by selecting the zone in the list and clicking on <guibutton>Delete Zone</guibutton>. You may
  also alter the ordering of the zones by selecting one from the list and using the 
  <guibutton>up</guibutton> and <guibutton>down</guibutton> buttons on the right.
</para>

<para>
  How zones are implemented differs from radio to radio. For example, some radios allow to set a
  different zone for each VFO (A or B), consequently these zones are simple lists of channels.
  Other radios allow to select a single zone for both VFOs. For these radios, a zone
  consists of two lists of channels. One for each VFO. <application>qdmr</application> zones follow
  the second approach. That is, a zone consists of two lists. One of each VFO. When programming 
  radios that support only one channel list per zone, the zone is split into two (unless the second 
  list is empty). One of each VFO.
</para>

<para>
  Double-clicking a zone or clicking on the <guibutton>Add Zone</guibutton> button will open the 
  zone editor dialog.
</para>

<screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="fig/qdmr-edit-zone.png" width="7cm" align="center"/></imageobject>
    <textobject>Screen-shot of the edit-zone dialog.</textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 <title>The zone editor.</title>
</screenshot>

<para>
  This dialog allows to add, remove and change the order of the channels within the zone.
</para>

</section>

  